(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.1",
"generated_at": "2026-07-26T04:41:37.764688",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.1-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
ぶっ壊せ その殻を
Break that shell
塗り替えてゆくんだ my way
I'll rewrite my way
迷いなど捨てて進め
Discard hesitation and move forward
幾千の夜を越えてゆけ
Surpass thousands of nights
光る未来へ飛び出せ
Fly out toward the shining future
目覚めた感情が
The awakened emotions
身体中を駆け巡る
Race through my entire body
恐れるものなんてない
There is nothing to fear
今こそがその時
Now is the very moment
熱く燃える鼓動を感じて
Feel the burning heartbeat
限界の壁を打ち破れ
Break through the wall of limits
信じる道を進み続けろ
Keep pushing down the path you believe in
眩いステージへ
To the dazzling stage
涙を拭いて顔を上げて
Wipe your tears and lift your face
描いた夢を叶えるまで
Until you fulfill the dream you drew
止まらずに走り抜けろ
Run through without stopping
私だけのストーリー
My own story
ぶっ壊せ その殻を
Break that shell
塗り替えてゆくんだ my way
I'll rewrite my way
光る未来へ飛び出せ
Fly out toward the shining future
私たちの物語
Our story
ぶっ壊せ その殻を
Break that shell
塗り替えてゆくんだ my way
I'll rewrite my way
迷いなど捨てて進め
Discard hesitation and move forward
幾千の夜を越えてゆけ
Surpass thousands of nights
光る未来へ飛び出せ
Fly out toward the shining future
目覚めた感情が
The awakened emotions
身体中を駆け巡る
Race through my entire body
恐れるものなんてない
There is nothing to fear
今こそがその時
Now is the very moment
熱く燃える鼓動を感じて
Feel the burning heartbeat
限界の壁を打ち破れ
Break through the wall of limits
ストレート ドキドキする
Straight, my heart is pounding
視線はまるでレーザービーム
Your gaze is like a laser beam
心をシュワリと突き刺すの
It pierces my heart with a fizzing sting
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
実る果実が水を弾いて キラキラしてる光に似てる
The ripe fruit repels water, resembling glittering light
グラウンドに立つキミの姿が まぶしくて 少し照れちゃうけど
Your figure standing on the ground is dazzling, making me a bit shy
ストレート まっすぐだね
Straight, it is straight
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム
Love is surely a laser beam
心をシュワリと突き刺すの
It pierces my heart with a fizzing sting
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
ストレート まっすぐだね
Straight, it is straight
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム
Love is surely a laser beam
心をシュワリと突き刺すの
It pierces my heart with a fizzing sting
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
ふたりを繋ぐ 秘密の光
The secret light connecting the two of us
あの日見つけた 秘密の光
The secret light we found that day
恋の瞬間 音は止まって
The moment of love, sound stops
時間はスローリーに 恋の光線
Time passes slowly, a ray of love
ストレート まっすぐだね
Straight, it is straight
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム
Love is surely a laser beam
心をシュワリと突き刺すの
It pierces my heart with a fizzing sting
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
ストレート まっすぐだね
Straight, it is straight
恋愛はきっとレーザービーム
Love is surely a laser beam
心をシュワリと突き刺すの
It pierces my heart with a fizzing sting
虹色のラブビーム
A rainbow-colored love beam
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Come on over, come take a look!
始まりましたなでしこ新衣装めぐり3Dライブ 今夜はまだまだこれから 皆さん一緒に盛り上がっていきましょう！
Our new Nadeshiko outfit 3D live has begun! Tonight is just getting started, let's get hyped together!
尽きない好奇心 素晴らしいジャポニズムに触れて
With endless curiosity, touching wonderful Japonism
令和の風雲児 皆様にお届け致しましょう
Let us deliver the children of the Reiwa storm to everyone!
饒舌に情熱 伝えたい愛に溢れている
Overflowing with eloquence, passion, and love to convey
無知の知がきっと 素敵な始まりになるんだよ
The knowledge of ignorance will surely make a wonderful beginning
知って欲しい たらふく味わって
I want you to know, to taste your fill
尊い人生 紐解いた歴史に 心惹かれていく
A precious life, drawn to the unraveled history
遥か遠く電波に乗って あなたまで この想い純粋に伝えたい
Riding the radio waves from afar, I want to purely convey this feeling to you
新しい世界 見せてあげる 開口一番 やっちゃって
I'll show you a new world, let's start off with a bang!
破天荒に型破って 打ち立てる 金字塔
Breaking the mold with wild abandon, building a monument
パンチライン 時を超え 出囃子に乗せて
Crossing time with a punchline, carried on our entrance music
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Come on over, come take a look!
浪漫を抱いた人生を 丸ごと賭けて傾きましょう
Risking it all on a life embraced with romance, let's live boldly.
刹那に生きた足跡を 偉大な先人と共に
Following the footprints of ephemeral lives alongside the great forebears.
洒落た口火切って手招き 藝事の深淵
Lighting a stylish spark, beckoning into the abyss of the performing arts.
相反する感情 愛憎超えていく感動
Contradictory feelings, emotion transcending love and hate.
遥か遠く世界越え宇宙まで この想い果てなく届けたい
Far away, across the world and into space, I want to send this endless feeling.
オリエンタル オクシデンタル どちらも愛しちゃって
Oriental, occidental—loving both of them,
揺き立てる衝動が加速する 創造の世界へと飛び込んで
the stirring impulse accelerates, leaping into the world of creation.
小喋に乗せ 寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
Riding on chatter, come closer and take a look!
語り継いでく人世の想い あなたの心に寄り添って
The thoughts of human life passed down through generations, snuggling close to your heart.
道楽主義で小粋にいなせ そんな生き様如何ですか？
Living stylishly with a hedonistic philosophy—how do you like such a way of life?
遥か遠く電波に乗ってあなたまで この想い純粋に伝えたい
Riding far radio waves all the way to you, I want to purely convey this feeling.
新しい世界見せてあげる 開口一番やっちゃって
Showing you a brand new world, starting right off with a bang,
破天荒に型破って打ち立てる 金字塔パンチライン時を超え
breaking the mold wildly to erect a monumental punchline across time.
出囃子に乗せ 寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい 寄ってらっしゃい見てらっしゃい
Riding on the entrance music, come closer and take a look!
はい、ということで…始まりました！儒烏風亭らでん新衣装お披露目ライブ――！ありがとうございます！
Yes, and with that... it has begun! Juufuutei Raden's new outfit reveal 3D live! Thank you so much!
皆様、改めてましてこんばんは！ホロライブデバイスはReGLOSSの室…じゃなくて、美術館プリンセス担当！
Good evening once again, everyone! Hololive... wait, ReGLOSS's Mu... no, Museum Princess in charge,
十日亭一門は前座に倣い…じゃなくて、儒烏風亭一門でございます！みんな来てくれてありがとうございます！
Juufuutei family following the opening act... no, it's Juufuutei family! Thank you everyone for coming!
本日のハッシュタグは、ハッシュタグ #らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ でいっぱいポストしてくれるととても嬉しいです。よろしくお願いします！
Today's hashtag is #RadenNewOutfit3DLive. I'd be so happy if you post a lot. Thank you!
ちょっと待ってね。『大丈夫？』って言われてました。大丈夫です、ありがとうございます！
Wait a second. People were asking 'Are you okay?' I'm okay, thank you!
さあ、今回ね…えー、らでん3Dお披露目ライブ…新衣装お披露目ライブ、ミラクル十代発表祭り！
Now, this time... um, Raden's 3D reveal live... new outfit reveal live, Miracle Teen Announcement Festival!
タイトルにもある通り、何やら十代発表があるとかないとか。しかも一つだけじゃないの！
As the title says, there are seemingly some teen announcements or maybe not. And not just one!
ということで、今日はね、ぜひ最後までお楽しみください！
And with that, please enjoy today all the way to the end!
さあ、そして皆さん気になってますよね？この新衣装、いかがですかーー！
Now, and everyone's curious, right? How is this new outfit?!
どう？みんなどうかな？これが私、らでんの新衣装ミュージアムプリンセス衣装です！
How is it? What do you all think? This is my new outfit, Raden's Museum Princess outfit!
ちょっとね、今日ね、ラグがね、ちょっとコメントとラグがあってあれなんですけれども。よーい？よーい？ありがと！ありがとうございます！
Um, today, there's a bit of lag with the comments, but... Ready? Ready? Thank you! Thank you so much!
えー、今回はですね、100万人記念ということで、さくらしおり先生にお仕立ていただきました！いえーい！
Um, this time, to commemorate 1 million subscribers, Sakura Shiori-sensei tailored this for me! Yay!
これもね、普段から応援してくださっている皆様のおかげです。本当にありがとう！ありがとうございます！
This is all thanks to everyone who supports me every day. Thank you so much! Thank you!
もちろんね、このライブのあと、アンコールライブっていうのが別件で…あるんですけれども、そこでまたのんびりとこのお召しについて、詳しく見ていきたいと思いますので、気になるよって方はぜひ…
Of course, after this live, there's an encore live session separately... so we'll leisurely take a closer look at this outfit there, so if you're curious...
メンバーシップの方に加入していただければと思います。
We hope you'll consider joining our membership.
今日ねお昼ぐらいにメンバーの方が使えるスタンプも追加されましたので、ぜひコメント欄でよかったら使ってみてください。
Today around noon, stamps that members can use were added, so please feel free to use them in the comment section.
もうみんな使いたくてたまらないアロワナスタンプとかが追加されてるので、ぜひみなさんねコメント欄いっぱいいアロワナを泳がせてください。よろしくお願いします！
Since arowana stamps and others that everyone's dying to use have been added, please let lots of arowanas swim in the comments section! Thank you!
さあということで、お召し物改めて新衣装なんですが、
Now then, to talk about my outfit, it's a new outfit once again,
今回衣装の他にちょっとね、1つ
and besides this outfit, I also made...
とあるものを作っちゃいましたよ。
...created a certain something.
ま、楽曲中にもね出てきたんですけれどもちぇんじゃかちぇんちぇんちぇんちぇん……じゃーん！素敵でございます！
Well, it appeared in the song too... ta-da! Isn't it wonderful?
いいでしょこれ？かっこいいでしょ？
Isn't this nice? Isn't it cool?
今回ね、特中でステッキ作っちゃった！
This time, I had a special staff made!
しかもこれだけじゃないんですよ。
And that's not all.
見ててね。レーザービームだ！すごい！
Watch this. A laser beam! Amazing!
今回ね、あのレーザービームも出せるようにしてもらいました。
This time, I was able to make it shoot laser beams too.
ぶんぶんぶんぶんぶんぶんぶんぶん…
Vroom vroom vroom...
もう大丈夫です。笑
Alright, that's enough. Haha.
疲れちゃった。ま、今日はね、ライブまだまだこれからですので、体力は温存していかないと。でも今日は自分の体力が出し切るまで全力でライブするからみんな応援よろしくね！
I'm tired. Well, today's live is still just beginning, so I have to conserve my stamina. But today I'm going to give it my all until I run out of stamina, so everyone please support me!
それではそろそろ次の曲に行きたいと思います。
Now then, I'd like to move on to the next song.
さあ、次の曲は何なのか？新衣装とは何なのか？ワクワクしながら聞いてくださいね。
Now, what is the next song? What is the new outfit? Please listen with excitement.
そしてここからはゲストも登場します！ゲストパートは収録になりますので、お楽しみにー！
And from here on, guests will also appear! The guest part will be prerecorded, so look forward to it!
それでは今夜はまだまだ始まったばかり、みんなで一緒に楽しみましょう！
Well, tonight has just begun, let's all enjoy it together!
それではどうぞー！
And here we go!
そう高く果てなく
So high and endless,
明日へと導くよ
leading to tomorrow.
私だけの光放ちたい DIVE!
I want to release my own light, DIVE!
自信なくしてただ 心に鍵かけて
I had lost my confidence and just locked my heart,
響く自分の声に 耳塞いでた
closing my ears to the voice echoing within me.
本当はいつだって わかっていたんだよ
Actually, I knew it all along—
一番大切なものが ここにあること
that the most important thing is right here.
無限に広がる宇宙(そら) 迷わず進もう
Let's move forward without hesitation into the endless sky!
Go! Fly! Yes! So high!
目を閉じて 言い聞かせてみだってもう
Close your eyes, even if you tell yourself...
からだ中騒いでる 止まらない heart
your whole body is restless. An unstoppable heart,
強く熱く...!!
strong and hot...!!
そう高く果てなく
So high and endless,
抱きしめた未来が 軌跡になる
the future I held in my arms becomes a path.
生まれた想いが 明日へと導くよ
The feelings that were born will lead to tomorrow.
私だけの光放ちたい DIVE!
I want to release my own light, DIVE!
目を閉じて 言い聞かせてみだってもう
Close your eyes, and even if you try to talk yourself into it,
からだ中騒いでる 止まらない heart
your whole body is restless. An unstoppable heart,
強く熱く...!!
strong and hot...!!
そう高く果てなく
So high and endless,
抱きしめた未来が 軌跡になる
the future I held in my arms becomes a path.
生まれた想いが 明日へと導くよ
The feelings that were born will lead to tomorrow.
私だけの光放ちたい DIVE!
I want to release my own light, DIVE!
そう高く果てなく
So high and endless,
抱きしめた未来が 軌跡になる
the future I held in my arms becomes a path.
Go! Fly! Yes! So high!
誰のものでもない 心に問いかけて
It doesn't belong to anyone, asking my heart,
選んだ道の先へと まっすぐに
straight ahead to the destination of the path I chose.
どんな時だって 見失わないよ
Whatever happens, I won't lose sight of it,
一番大切な場所を 見つけたから
because I found the place that is most important.
遠回りでもいい 胸張って進もう
It's okay to take a detour, let's move forward with pride.
Louder! Sing! Louder!
不器用かな でも傷ついたって構わないよ
I might be clumsy, but I don't care if I get hurt.
曇りない気持ちで 生きたい pride 私らしく...!!
With cloudless feelings, I want to live proudly in my own way...!!
両手を広げて 解き放した昨日が 翼になる
Spread your hands, the yesterday I released becomes wings.
重ねた出会いが この瞬間彩るよ
The encounters I accumulated color this moment.
私だけの光信じて DIVE!
Believe in my own light, DIVE!
この瞬間
This moment,
この時
this time,
いろどるよ
it paints the color.
私だけの光 信じて
Believe in my own unique light.
DIVE!
そら高く
High into the sky,
はてなく
endlessly,
抱きしめた未来が 奇跡になる
the future we held close becomes a miracle.
生まれた想いが
The feelings that were born
明日へと導くよ
will guide us toward tomorrow.
私だけの光 放ちダイ
Unleashing my own unique light—
DIVE!
WOW
Woah...
JAPANの美術史♪
JAPAN Art History
絵画に立体！
(Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史♪
JAPAN Art History
テストもバッチリ！
(Even tests are a breeze!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！
O-bo-e-ma-SHOW!
は～い皆さんこんにちは！美術史を学ぶ時間です！
Hi everyone, hello! It's time to learn art history!
まずは縄文弥生古墳までやってみよう！
Let's start with Jomon, Yayoi, and Kofun periods!
焔型土器、遮光器土偶、
Flame-style pottery, dogu with snow-goggle eyes,
縄文のビーナス！
Jomon Venus!
銅鐸、銅戈、銅矛、銅剣、弥生土器！
Dotaku, doka, dobu, doken, Yayoi pottery!
埴輪も色々、踊る人々、掛甲武人、馬型埴輪！
Various haniwa, dancing people, armored warriors, horse haniwa!
古墳出土の鉄刀、鉄剣、七支刀に土師器須恵器！
Iron swords, seven-branched swords, Haji and Sue ware!
OKOKOKOK OKいい感じ！
OK, OK, OK, OK, looking good!
次は飛鳥に奈良時代！
Next is the Asuka and Nara periods!
さん！に！いち！ごー！
Three! Two! One! Go!
仏像いっぱい 釈迦如来、菩薩と合わせて三尊像！
Lots of Buddha statues, Shaka Nyorai, and Bodhisattvas making a triad!
玉虫厨子、天寿国繍帳、金堂壁画、古墳壁画！
Tamamushi Shrine, Tenjukoku Mandala, Kondo and tumulus murals!
東大寺には奈良の大仏、興福寺には阿修羅像！
Great Buddha of Nara at Todai-ji, Asura statue at Kofuku-ji!
音と一緒に遊びましょう！螺鈿紫檀五絃琵琶！
Let's play with sound! Raden Shitan Gogen Biwa!
未来のキミに届くように 紡いでいこう この想い
Weaving these feelings so they reach you in the future.
愛さえあれば大丈夫 語り合う時が来るまで
As long as there is love, it'll be alright until we talk together.
JAPANの美術史♪
JAPAN Art History
絵画に立体！
(Paintings and sculptures!)
JAPANの美術史♪
JAPAN Art History
テストもバッチリ！
(Even tests are a breeze!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！
O-bo-e-ma-SHOW!
まだまだ色々ございます がんばってついてきてくださいね
There's still plenty more, so do your best to keep up!
平安鎌倉南北朝 参る！
Heian, Kamakura, Nanbokucho periods, here we come!
曼荼羅、一木造り、寄木造り！
Mandala, ichiboku-zukuri, yosegi-zukuri!
鳥獣人物戯画に 源氏物語！
Choju-giga and The Tale of Genji!
平等院鳳凰堂阿弥陀如来坐像！
Amida Nyorai seated statue at Byodoin Phoenix Hall!
模様がとってもかわいい 片輪車螺鈿手箱！
Katawachuraden tebako with super cute patterns!
東大寺の南大門の金剛力士像！
Kongorikishi statues at the Nandaimon gate of Todai-ji!
阿弥陀二十五菩薩来迎図、山越阿弥陀図！
Raigo of the Twenty-Five Bodhisattvas, Amida over the Mountains!
蒙古襲来絵詞、空也上人像！
Mongol Invasion Scroll, statue of Saint Kuya!
一遍聖絵伝、後三年合戦絵巻！
Illustrated Biography of Saint Ippen, Gosannen Kassen Emaki!
YOYO! 半分くらい来たぜ多分 まだまだいくぜありのまま
YOYO! We're about halfway there, still going strong just as we are!
室町から安土桃山！
From Muromachi to Azuchi-Momoyama!
能面翁に枯山水、天橋立図、呂洞賓図、狩野派の屏風！
Noh mask Okina, dry landscape garden, Amanohashidate, Luhongbin, Kano school screens!
曜変天目茶碗、洛中洛外図屏風！
Yohen Tenmoku tea bowl, Rakuchu-Rakugai-zu byobu!
唐獅子図屏風、松鷹図、職人尽図、花下遊楽図、松林図、山水図に
Karajishi-zu byobu, Matsutaka-zu, Shokunin-zukushi-zu, Kashu-yuraku-zu, Shorin-zu, Sansui-zu...
八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱！
Yatsuhashi maki-e raden suzuribako!
未来のキミに届くように 紡いでいこう この想い
Weaving these feelings so they reach you in the future.
愛さえあれば大丈夫 語り合う時が来るまで
As long as there is love, it'll be alright until we talk together.
ここまでついてきてくれてありがとう！ あとちょっと、最後まで頑張ろう！
Thank you for following along this far! Just a little more, let's do our best!
江戸時代から昭和まで！いくよ！
From the Edo period to the Showa era! Here we go!
さん！に！いち！GO！
Three! Two! One! GO!
舟橋蒔絵硯箱、風神雷神図屏風！
Funabashi maki-e suzuribako, Fujin Raijin-zu byobu!
燕子花図屏風、見返り美人！
Kakitsubata-zu byobu, Mikaeri Bijin!
好色一代男、奥の細道
Koshoku Ichidai Otoko, Oku no Hosomichi
奥の細道、
Oku no Hosomichi,
富嶽三十六景、
Thirty-six Views of Mount Fuji,
東海道中膝栗毛
The Fifty-three Stations of the Tokaido.
老猿、ゆみ、坑夫、
Old Ape, Yuami, Kofu,
墓守、伎芸天、
Hakasou, Gigeiten,
竜虎図、黒き猫、
Ryuko-zu, Black Cat,
鮭、海の幸
Salmon, Bounty of the Sea,
渡頭の夕暮
Evening Sun on Crossing,
麗子微笑、紫禁城
Reiko Smiling, The Forbidden City,
班猫、五浦釣人
Banneko, Go-Ura Fisher,
太陽の塔
Tower of the Sun,
吉原治良の円
Yoshihara Jiro's Circle,
東山魁夷の道
Higashiyama Kaii's Path.
未来のキミに届くように
To reach the kiis of the future,
繋いでいこう　この想い
Let's keep connecting these feelings.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there's love, it'll be alright,
語り合おう　朝が来るまで
Until the morning we can talk comes.
未来まで
Until the future,
JAPANの美術史♪（アート！アート！）
JAPAN's Art History! (Art! Art!)
JAPANの美術史♪（絵画に立体！）
JAPAN's Art History! (Painting to 3D!)
JAPANの美術史♪（テストもバッチリ！）
JAPAN's Art History! (Test is also a breeze!)
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！ありがとう！
O-bo-e-ma-SHOW! Thank you!
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは。
To everyone watching the live stream, welcome.
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここでらでんのこぼなし美術解説の時間です！
It's time for Raden's story art history lecture!
なんと今回ご紹介するのは…
And what we're introducing today is...
こちらでん！じゃじゃーん！国宝「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」ということで、
this! Tada! National Treasure, "Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Suzuri-bako"!
今回特別に東京国立博物館さんから3Dモデルをお借りしましたー！
We have specially borrowed a 3D model from the Tokyo National Museum!
ゆほ、みんなにもよく見てもらいましょう、こちらでございます！こちらがバーチャル八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱です。
Let's take a closer look, everyone. Here it is! This is the Virtual Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Suzuri-bako.
らでんってなんかどっかで聞いたことがありますね、なんかそんな名前のバーチャルユーチューバーがいるような、いないような。
"Raden"... Have I heard that name somewhere before? Like, a virtual YouTuber with that name... wait, no.
こちらは私のオリジナル曲「JAPANの美術史おぼえまSHOW」にも登場する作品です。
This is a work that also appears in my original song, "JAPAN's Art History Oboemashou."
どうですか皆さんこの輝きとデザイン！大胆かつ花びらの装飾の細かい部分も美しいこちらの作品。作ったのは尾形光琳という人です。
What do you think of this radiance and design, everyone? The fine details of the blooming and scattering iris petals are so gorgeous. This work was created by Ogata Korin.
これがこの硯箱を作ったのは江戸時代なんですが、どこかモダンな要素も感じることができます。
He created this suzuri-bako in the Edo period, but you can feel some modern elements in it too.
さて、工芸品を見るとき様々な見方がありますが、手助けになるのは作品名です。
Now, when looking at crafts, there are various ways to appreciate them, but what will help is the title of the work.
ではスライドいきます。
So let's go to the slide.
この工芸品の名前復習しましょう。「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」。漢字がたくさん入っていますが、1つ1つ紐解いていきます。
Let's review the name of this craft: "Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Suzuri-bako." It has a lot of kanji, so let's break it down one by one.
まずは「八橋」。日本美術史における工芸品は物語の1場面や和歌、歌ですね、がテーマになっていることが少なくありません。
First is "Yatsuhashi." In Japanese art, crafts often take scenes from stories like "The Tale of Ise" or waka poetry as their theme.
そしてこの硯箱もその1つ。『伊勢物語』第九段三河国八橋の場面が主題になっているんですよ。
And this suzuri-bako is one of them. It's based on "The Tale of Ise, 9th Section: Mikawa Province Yatsuhashi."
なのでこれは橋ですね。
So this is a "hashi" (bridge).
八橋、この場面に出てくる八つの橋のこと、つまりは何を描いたかを表しています。
"Yatsuhashi" refers to the eight-plank bridge appearing in this scene, and it expresses what is being depicted.
では何をえがいたかが分かったら次ににどんな技法が使われたかそれを表すのが蒔絵そしてらでんです。
So, once we know what is depicted, next we look at what technique was used. That's expressed by "maki-e" and "raden."
蒔絵とは簡単に言うと、金の粉を漆という接着剤を用いて貼り付けたもの。ここで言うと、かきつばたの葉の部分ですね、ピュンピュンてなってる部分です。
Simply put, "maki-e" is a lacquer craft technique where gold or silver powder is adhered using urushi as an adhesive. Here, it's used for the leaves of the irises.
次に螺鈿とは貝の光沢を持つ部分を薄くして貼り付ける加飾法。「螺」は巻き貝をさし、「鈿」にはかざるという意味がある。この作品に使われているのはアワビ貝で、花びらを表現するためにあえて穴の開いた貝を使用しているのが分かります。
Next, "raden" is a technique where the lustrous part of a shell is thinned and pasted on. Here, it's used for the iris flowers, and they deliberately used pierced shells to represent the petals.
そして最後にそもそもこれは何か？それを表すのが硯箱です。
And finally, what is this in the first place? That's expressed by "suzuri-bako" (inkstone box).
え、真ん中ご覧ください。こちら、え、墨汁を作る硯入れが上の段にあり、それにその下の、え、下の段は用紙紙入れになっています。
Take a look at the middle. Here, the inkstone tray for making ink is on the upper tier, and below that is the paper storage area.
さあこれで「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」の言葉の紐解きが完了しましたね。
So now the tracing of the words for "Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Suzuri-bako" is complete.
かきつばたが咲く川にかかる橋のダイナミックな魅力にも大注目なのがこの硯箱。パカッと開けると、波が描かれています。
The dynamic appeal of the bridge over the irises—opening this suzuri-bako reveals waves painted inside.
もうここまで聞いたらなぜそこに波の意匠を施したのか皆さんならお分かりですね。上の段にある橋の下の
By now, you probably all understand why waves are applied on the lower tier beneath the bridge!
なみということでですね、
So, as I was saying...
え、実はですね、こちらの「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」
Actually, this "Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Inkstone Box"
普段展示される際は、箱を閉じた状態なんですよ。
is normally displayed with the box closed.
つまり、中の様子をご覧いただけるのはこの配信ならではの貴重な機械です。
That means being able to see inside is a precious opportunity unique to this stream!
こちらがなんと、2026年5月26日から8月16日、本館2室にて展示されるとのことです。
And amazingly, it will be exhibited in Room 2 of the Main Building from May 26 to August 16, 2026!
東京国立博物館さんで是非見てみていただければと思います！
I hope you'll all go check it out at the Tokyo National Museum!
このね、波のね、細かいところがすごく、これ筆でやってるんですよ。
Look at how detailed these waves are. They do this with a brush, you know.
筆でこうやって、あ、お時間となってしまいました。
Doing it like this with a brush—ah, we're out of time.
それでは皆さん、また次回お会い致しましょう。
Well then everyone, let's meet again next time.
未来の君に届くように つないでいくこの想い
Reaching out to the future you, these connected feelings
会いたえあれば大丈夫 語り合おう 朝が来るまで
If we can meet, it'll be alright, let's talk until morning comes
ということて、なんと私、儒烏風亭らでんと
And so, amazingly, I, Juufuutei Raden,
東京国立博物館さんとのコラボが決定しました！
and the Tokyo National Museum have decided to collaborate!
すごーい！みんなやったよー！
So amazing! Everyone, we did it!
でもね、らでん配信とかもういろんなところで、東博さんがねずっと大好きだって言ってたんですけども！
But you know, on my streams and in various places, I've always said how much I love Tohaku!
今回ね、念願の東白らでんコラボでございます！すごい！
This time, our long-cherished Tohaku-Raden collaboration is happening! Amazing!
あら、東博、最近名前聞きましたね、そうです！
Oh, you've heard the name Tohaku recently? That's right!
え、先日ね10月から京都、1月から東京にて開催予定の特別展「源氏物語 王朝のかがやき」展の音声ガイドのスペシャル・トラックをつとめさせていただくことが発表されましたが、
It was announced that I will be in charge of the special tracks for the audio guide of the special exhibition "The Tale of Genji: Radiant Culture of the Japanese Imperial Court," to be held in Kyoto from October and Tokyo from January!
これね、これチラシね。なんとこの特別展、源氏物語展の東京会場となる東京国立博物館さんと、あ、ごめんなさい！
And this, look at the flyer. Amazingly, this special exhibition, the Tokyo venue of The Tale of Genji Exhibition, with the Tokyo National Museum—ah, I'm sorry!
東京国立博物館様とのコラボが決定いたしました！すごーい！
Our collaboration with the Tokyo National Museum has been decided! So amazing!
開催時期はこの源氏物語展と同じ2027年1月に実施予定となっております！
The collaboration period is scheduled for January 2027, the same time as the Genji exhibition!
なんて、こっちは「源氏物語展×儒烏風亭らでんコラボ」、そして同じ1月に、えー東京国立博物館×儒烏風亭らでんコラボがあるとな。
So, this one is "The Tale of Genji Exhibition × Juufuutei Raden Collaboration," and also in January, um, there's the Tokyo National Museum × Juufuutei Raden Collaboration.
もっと簡単に言うと、来年の1月は東博のいろんなところにらでんちゃんがね、出物しちゃいまーすっていう感じです！
To put it simply, next January, Raden-chan will pop up all over Tohaku! That's the vibe!
こちら詳細はですね、また続報をお待ちいただければと思います！すごいですよ！すごいすごい！
Please look forward to further details on this! It's amazing! So amazing!
ということで、本日の重大発表1つ目は、えー東博儒烏風亭らでんコラボでございました！みんなありがとーーう！
So, the first major announcement today was the Tohaku Juufuutei Raden Collaboration! Thank you everyone!
さあ、ライブも重大発表もまだまだ続きます。
Now, the live and major announcements will continue.
ちょっと待って、ちょっと疲れちゃった。
Wait a minute, I got a little tired.
といことでね、あの、東博、もともとらでんが日本美術史に興味持ったのって東博さんで能面を見て、そのときに「ああ、なんて美しいんだ！」って思ったし、
So, you see, Tohaku—originally, what sparked my interest in Japanese art history was seeing Noh masks at Tohaku, and thinking, "Ah, how beautiful!" at that time.
らでんて日本で生まれ育ったのに日本のこと本当になんだ知らないんだなって思ったのがきっかけで、
And realizing that even though I was born and raised in Japan, I really knew nothing about Japan—that was the catalyst.
そっからなんだかんだあって日本美術史勉強したりして、なんやかんやあって、ホロライブに入って、なんやかんやあって今こんな素敵な衣装をお披露目して、なんやかんやあってこんなありがたいコラボをさせていただける事になりました！みんなのおかげだよ、ありがとうーー！
From there, through various things, I studied Japanese art history, joined Hololive, debuted this wonderful outfit, and now I'm able to have this amazing collaboration! It's all thanks to you guys, thank you so much!
もう人生本当に何が起こるかわかりません。もうとんでもない何がどう未来へ繋がっていくのかみたいなことももうわかりません。人生は奇妙なボケみたいなもんでございますな。
You really never know what will happen in life. I have no idea how things will connect to the future. Life is like a strange punchline.
さあ、ということでそろそろ次の曲に行きたいと思います。それでは聞いてください、「ココロパズルリズム」。
Well then, I'd like to move on to the next song shortly. Please listen to "Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm."
はあ ココロパズルリズム
Ah, Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm
はあ
Ah...
ああ…
これからの未来 ほら たくさんのピース
Future to come, look, so many pieces
組み立てるのはキミしだい 一つずつの
Putting them together is up to you, piece by piece,
明日を生きる ココロのパズルとリズム
living tomorrow with the puzzle and rhythm of the heart.
うまくは言えないけれど
Though I can't put it well into words,
不思議と安心していられる感覚って
this strangely comforting feeling
まるでパズルみたいだ
is just like a puzzle.
もうずっと前からの
Ever since long ago,
僕らは予約席
we've had reserved seats.
さあ 両手つないで
Come on, holding hands both hands,
きっと一つになれる
we can surely become one.
完成が見えていいても
Even when the completion is in sight,
すんなりとはいかないね
things don't always go smoothly, do they?
それぞれが夢のカケラだね
Each one is a piece of a dream.
これからの未来
Future to come,
ほら たくさんのピース
look, so many pieces,
組み立てるのはキミしだい 一つずつの
putting them together is up to you, piece by piece,
明日を生きる 空いた隙間を埋める
living tomorrow, filling the empty gaps.
楽しいこともあるきっとあるけど
There are surely joyful times too, but
それよりも大切なのは
even more important than that
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
are the times when we're sad or happy,
一緒に泣ける そんな ココロのパズル
and can cry together—that's the heart's puzzle.
すんなりとはいかないね
Things don't go smoothly, do they?
キミと僕のパズルの行方も
The whereabouts of your and my puzzle too.
これからのlove story ほら たくさんのピース
Our future love story, look, so many pieces.
間違うこともあるけど 胸に刻み
There are mistakes too, engraved in our chests,
明日を生きる 空いた隙間を埋める
living tomorrow, filling the empty gaps.
楽しいこともあるきっとあるけど
There are surely joyful times too, but
それよりも大切なのは
even more important than that
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに 一緒に泣ける そんな ココロのパズル
are the times when we're sad or happy, and can cry together—that's the heart's puzzle.
ああ…
Ah...
繋いで it's a nice day
Connected, it's a nice day.
これからの未来
Future to come,
ほら たくさんのピース
look, so many pieces,
組み立てるのはキミしだい 一つずつの
putting them together is up to you, piece by piece,
明日を生きる 空いた隙間を埋める
living tomorrow, filling the empty gaps.
楽しいこともあるきっとあるけど
There are surely joyful times too, but
それよりも大切なのは
even more important than that
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに 一緒に泣ける そんな ココロのパズル
are the times when we're sad or happy, and can cry together—that's the heart's puzzle.
ココロのパズル
The heart's puzzle.
ああ…
Ah...
ライブをご覧になっている皆さま、こんばんは！
Good evening to everyone watching the live stream!
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここでらでんのお話し美術解説の時間です！
We're in the middle of the live, but now it's time for Raden's art talk and commentary!
今回ご紹介するのは…
What we're introducing this time is...
こちらでーん！じゃじゃーん！
Right here! Ta-da!
クロード・モネ「睡蓮の池」
Claude Monet's "Water Lily Pond"
今回なんとロンドンのナショナルギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしております！
We've borrowed images from the National Gallery in London!
本当にありがとうございます！
Thank you so much!
皆さんどうですか？
How is everyone liking it?
私モネの描く世界が大好きなんです。
I just love the world Monet paints.
ま、モネといえば日本でもとても人気の高い画家ですが
Well, speaking of Monet, he's very popular in Japan too,
彼の絵画の魅力はどのようなところにあるのでしょうか？
but what makes his paintings so charming?
今回は彼の絵画に内包する魅力を言語化していきましょう！
Today, let's put the charm in his art into words!
この作品は1899年頃描かれました。
This work was painted around 1899.
緑色の光が溢れる睡蓮の池には大きな橋が掛かり、橋の奥には柳が描かれています。
In the pond overflowing with green light, a large bridge spans across, with weeping willows beyond.
実はこの場所、モネの自宅に作った池なんです。
Actually, this is a pond Monet made at his own home.
フランスのジヴェルニーという町に家を購入した彼は、近隣の川から水を引いて自分の理想とする庭を作りました。
After buying a house in Giverny, France, he drew water from a nearby river to build his ideal garden.
アーチ状の大きな橋、これいわゆる太鼓橋と呼ばれる橋と柳。
A large arched bridge—what's called a drum bridge—and weeping willows.
あれ？なんだか日本っぽさを感じませんか？
Huh? Don't you feel a somewhat Japanese vibe?
それもそのはず、彼は日本の浮世絵に強く影響を受けた画家でした。
That's right—he was strongly influenced by Japanese ukiyo-e.
彼の描く絵は光に溢れていて、目の前で風が吹いて水面が揺れているようにも見えます。
His paintings are filled with light, looking as though wind blows and water ripples before your eyes.
じっと見ていると水も花も木も橋も空気でさえも溶けていくようです、
Staring at it, even water, flowers, trees, bridges, and air seem to melt away,
見ていて落ち着く絵画だと思いませんか？
making it a soothing painting to look at.
モネは絵を描くとき、色を混ぜて塗るのではなく純粋な、何も混ざってない色を置くように塗りました。
When painting, rather than mixing colors, Monet applied pure, unmixed colors side by side.
色は混ぜれば混ぜるほど塗り重ねれば重ねるほど暗くなっていきます、彼はこの課題を色を置くことによって解決し、光で溢れた絵画の表現に成功したんです。
Colors darken the more they're mixed or layered. He solved this by placing pure colors, succeeding in expressing light-filled art.
この絵画に近づいてみると、筆跡がしっかり残っています。
Getting close to this painting, the brushstrokes remain very clear.
隣り合った絵の具一つ一つの相乗効果を計算し、絵の具の塊から温度感や湿度感を感じることができる風景へと変貌する表現はモネが生涯かけて研究していたものです。
Calculating the synergy of adjacent paints to evoke temperature and humidity from paint lumps was Monet's lifelong research.
光を求めたモネが陰影のない日本の浮世絵に強く惹かれたのも理解できますね。
It's clear why light-seeking Monet was drawn to unshaded Japanese ukiyo-e.
彼の絵画の明るさは画家としての研究の成果であり、情熱さえ感じられるそんな作品だと私は感じます。
The brightness of his paintings reflects artistic research and palpable passion.
みんなはこの絵画はどう読んだかな？
How did everyone interpret this painting?
実はモネは印象派の画家と呼ばれるきっかけを作った人でもあるんですが、それはまた別のお話。
Actually, Monet also sparked the Impressionist movement, but that's another story.
という感じでございまして、こちらはロンドンのナショナルギャラリーさんにて見ることができます、ぜひ行ってみてください！
That said, you can see this at the National Gallery in London—please check it out!
また次回！
See you next time!
I want to fight your brother
let's kung-fu
Every night I look to the skies
and wonder what we did
always a naive point of view
that breaks us
If I could find the meaning of it all
I'd take the chance maybe in time we'll walk the mile
and change it if we can
It's now and always
How did we get this far
Always
We're making a brand new start
Nothing will hold me down
Always
Wave goodbye to me!
Around the world 新しいことに
Around the world for something new
Around the world フミダスチカラで
Around the world with the power to take a step
Around the world 世界は変わるさ
Around the world the world will change
But don't run away 'cause if it's not ok!
I'll change that world into something better, honey!
let's kung-fu
果てなく広がるこの大地を 僕らはまた歩き続けるさ
Spreading endlessly, this great earth, we will keep walking again
果てしく広がるこの大地を 僕らはまた歩き続けるさ
We'll keep walking across this endlessly expanding land.
全ての意味が 分かるのならば
If we could understand the meaning of it all...
この瞳で 何を見つめるのだろう
What would these eyes be gazing at?
IT'S NOW AND ALWAYS
(HOW DID WE GET THIS FAR)
ALWAYS WE'RE MAKING A BRAND NEW START
ALWAYS NOTHING WILL HOLD ME DOWN
ALWAYS WAVE GOODBYE TO ME!
AROUND THE WORLD 君だけのために
Around the world, just for you.
AROUND THE WORLD 探し続けるよ
Around the world, I'll keep searching.
AROUND THE WORLD 奇跡のかけらを BUT DON'T RUN AWAY 'CAUSE IT'S NOT OK!
Around the world, searching for the fragments of miracles... But don't run away 'cause if it's not ok!
'CAUSE IT'S NOT OK! YOU KNOW IT'S GONNA BE
YEAH EY AND YOU KNOW IT'S GONNA BE RAINING AND YOU KNOW IT'S GONNA BE HARD
AS LONG AS WE TRUST EACH OTHER NOTHING'S GONNA BREAK APART OH NO! NO!
IF YA WANNA BE SOMEBODY GET UP ON YA FEET AND GO
I KNOW WE'RE GONNA MEET EACH OTHER SOMEWHERE AROUND THE GLOBE
AROUND THE WORLD いつでも自分に
Around the world, always to myself.
AROUND THE WORLD 負けている人は
Around the world, those who are defeated...
AROUND THE WORLD 何も掴めない
Around the world, can grasp nothing.
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY 'CAUSE IT'S NOT OK!
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY 'CAUSE IT'S NOT OK! I'LL CHANGE THAT WORLD INTO SOMETHING BETTER HONEY!
ふーっ、ふーっ、はいっ！
Whew... whew... yes!
ということで、なんと私、儒烏風亭らでんと… ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボが決定しましたーっ！
And with that... it has been decided that I, Juufutei Raden, am collaborating with The National Gallery, London!
ナショナル・ギャラリーさんといえば、もうね、ゴッホ、ターナー、もっとにかくいろんな画家さんたちの超有名作品がいっぱい所蔵されているところなんですが、なんとそんなナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボも、儒烏風亭らでんの瞳に映る世界の名画、あ、「Shared Art Journey」コラボ決定です！すごいー！
Speaking of The National Gallery, it houses so many ultra-famous works by various painters like Gogh, Turner, and so many others. And it's been decided that we're collaborating with them for "When Raden Meets Art: A Shared Art Journey"! Amazing!
さあこれね、とある3つの名画とコラボしてるんですが、みんなわかるかな？あ、3つね、3つあるんだけど。
Now, this collaborates with three specific famous paintings. Can everyone guess what they are? There are three of them.
え、では左からいきましょうか。え、左、ターナー《雨、蒸気、スピード、グレート・ウェスタン鉄道》、そして真ん中、モネの《睡蓮の池》、そして一番右、これみなさん分かるでしょう？ゴッホの《ひまわり》。
Let's go from the left. First, on the left: Turner's "Rain, Steam and Speed – The Great Western Railway". In the middle: Monet's "Water-Lilies". And on the far right, everyone probably knows this one? Van Gogh's "Sunflowers".
そして今回、え、コラボ商品が、ございます！全6種類あるんですよー！じゃ、1つずつね、ちょっと紹介していきましょう。
And this time, there are collaboration goods available! There are 6 types in total! Let's introduce them one by one.
えー、まず左上からいきましょうか。まずはフレグランスミストセットです。らでんが監修考案したフレグランスミスト、3点の名画が持つイメージを香りです表現しました！本商品はアルコールフリーのフレグランスミストなので、いろんな場面に合わせて使用可能です。
Let's start from the top left. First is the fragrance mist set. The fragrance mists supervised and devised by Raden express the image of the three paintings through scent! Since these are alcohol-free fragrance mists, they can be used in various situations.
じゃあ、隣いきましょうか。えー、その隣ローラーボールペン。3つの名画のエッセンスと儒烏風亭らでんの家紋を絶妙に融合させたデザインでございます。
Next, let's go next door. Next is the rollerball pen. The design exquisitely fuses the essence of the three paintings with Juufutei Raden's family crest.
えー、じゃあ次が、左下、カップ＆ソーサーセット。描き下ろしイラストからインスピレーションを得たボーンチャイナ製のカップ＆ソーサーセットでございます。ソーサーの中心には儒烏風亭らでんの名前も記載されています。せっかくらでんも紅茶飲めるようになったんで、お揃いにしましょうや！
Next, on the bottom left: the cup and saucer set. A bone china cup and saucer set inspired by the newly drawn illustrations. Juufutei Raden's name is also inscribed in the center of the saucer. Since Raden can now drink black tea, let's match with them!
えー、そしてその隣がスカーフ！新たに描き下ろしイラスト要素を組み合わせ…
And next to that is the scarf! Combining newly drawn illustration elements...
ファッション性と実用性を兼ね備えたデザインスカーフでございます。
Featuring a design that balances fashion and practicality, it's a designer scarf!
そしてじゃあその隣りが、え、アクリルスタンド！ホコラボならではの新規描きおろしアクリルスタンドでございます。
Next to that is the acrylic stand, featuring a brand-new illustration exclusive to Honkoro!
え、じゃあ右上行きましょう！キャンバスアート！描き下ろしイラストを使用されるキャンバスアートでございます。
Going up to the top right, we have canvas art, featuring newly drawn illustrations!
その下はトートバッグ！表面にはホコラボのために描き下ろされたイラスト、裏面には3点の絵画のディテールをあしらったデザインの両面仕様となっています。
Below that is the tote bag, featuring a newly drawn illustration on the front and details of three masterpieces on the back.
そして最後、ランダムクリアカードになります！全6種のランダムクリアカードで、一部のカードには箔押しデジタルサインと特別メッセージが入っていますよ。
And finally, we have the random clear cards, featuring all six designs, some of which include foil-stamped digital signatures and special messages!
グッズいいでしょう？どれも素敵でしょ！
Aren't the goods lovely? All of them are so nice!
そしてさらに、グッズだけではございません！
And that's not all for the goods.
ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボで、音声ガイドも収録させていただきましたー！すごい！
We've also recorded an audio guide in collaboration with The National Gallery in London! Amazing!
しかもこちらね、なんとラデンの公式チャンネルにてアップする予定でございますが、詳細は後日公開予定となりますので、続報をお待ちくださーい！
And what's more, this is scheduled to be uploaded to Raden's official channel, with details to be announced at a later date, so please look forward to it!
と、グッズとガイドと盛りだくさんなんですが、みんな、ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリー、どんなとこからか、ぶ、ぶ、ごめんなさい！
That's a lot of goods and guides, but do you all know what kind of place the National Gallery in London...
ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーどんなところか、気になりませんか？ロンドンの街並み、見てみたくないですか？
Doesn't it make you curious about what the cityscape of London looks like?
ということで、なんと実・は！
So, actually...
ReGLOSSメンバーでロンドンロケに行ってきましたーー！うおーー！
We went on a ReGLOSS location shoot in London! Woohoo!
そのロケの様子はReGLOSSチャンネルなどで後日公開予定となっておりますので、こちらもぜひお楽しみにー！
Footage of the shoot will be released on the ReGLOSS channel at a later date, so please look forward to that as well!
ということで、重大告知その2は、儒烏風亭らでんとロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボでございました！ありがとーー！
And with that, that's our second major announcement: a collaboration between Juufuutei Raden and the National Gallery in London! Thank you!
そしていま、スタッフさんの方から、どうやらいまXで、これXですか？Xでトレンド2位だそうです！すごい、みんなありがとーー！
And now, it looks like staff are saying... X is trending second! Amazing, thank you everyone!
大丈夫かな？トレンドに入った理由がらでんちゃんの体力手配で心配で、めっちゃ入ってたらどうしようかなって。でへへ。
I hope I'm doing okay... The reason I joined the trending topics is because I was worried about Raden's stamina, and I was thinking about what I'd do if I went too hard haha!
でも今日は、今日はもう体力がもうすっかりかになって、次の日動けなくなるまで頑張るってらでんは決めたんです。
But today, today I decided I'm going to give it my all until I'm totally exhausted and can't move the next day!
だから今日はみんなもね、いっぱいいっぱい楽しんでほしいです。どうですか皆さん、ついてこれてますかー？
So today, I want everyone to have as much fun as possible, too! How is everyone? Can you keep up with me?
あ、待ってくださいね！重大発表、まだあるんです！まだあるんです、これで終わりじゃないんですよ！しかもライブもまだまだ続きますので、みなさんチャンネルはそのままだよ！
Oh, wait a minute, our major announcements aren't over yet! There's still more! This isn't the end, you know! And the live stream is still going to continue, so everyone, keep watching the channel!
では、次の曲に行きたいと思います！それでは、だざ！
Now then, let's move on to the next song! Here we go!
水面に映った藍 眩しく揺れる
Indigo, reflected on the surface of the water, sways dazzlingly.
手探りで探してた 足りない私
I searched by touch for the missing parts of me.
ゆっくりと動き出した
Everything slowly began to move,
何万年も前からこの時を約束されていたみたいにほら
as if this moment had been promised to me tens of thousands of years ago, look.
風は歌い 雨は語り
The wind sings, the rain speaks,
たどり着くよ 光のすみかへ
I will reach the abode of the light.
幾重にも重なってる この地球の偶然
They are layered one on top of the other, the coincidences of this planet.
影の向こう 真実の色
Beyond the shadows is the true color.
見付け出すよ 光のすみかへ
I will find the abode of the light.
一つでも欠けていたら きっと出会えてなかったね
If even one thing were missing, I’m sure we would not have met.
飛べぬまま 見上げてた 透明な空から
Unable to fly I looked up and saw the gentle morning sun,
透明な空から
From the clear sky
真っ直ぐに
Straight
差し込んだ
Pierced
優しい朝日
A gentle morning sun
過ぎた季節が歪みに
The seasons that passed, distorted
削った今という瞬き
And carved away this instant called "now"
どこにも同じものはないの
There's nothing else like it anywhere
ほら 生きてる証
See, it's proof of being alive
風は歌い
The wind sings
雨は語り
The rain speaks
たどり着くよ
I'll reach it
光のすみかへ
To the dwelling of light
幾重にも重なってる
Layer upon layer, overlapping
地球の偶然
The coincidences of this planet
影の向こう
Beyond the shadow
真実の色
The true colors
見つけ出すよ
I will find
光のすみかを
The dwelling of light
一つでも欠けていたら
If even one thing had been missing
きっと出会えてなかったね
We surely would never have met
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは。
Good evening, everyone watching the live stream.
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここでラデンの小話美術解説の時間です！
Mid-way through the live stream, it's time for Raden's short art commentary!
今回ご紹介するのは、こちらジャン！フィンセント・ファン・ゴッホ「ひまわり」。
Today we are introducing this—ta-da! Vincent van Gogh's "Sunflowers".
今回ナショナルギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしております。ありがとうございます。
We have borrowed images from the National Gallery for this. Thank you very much.
ゴッホといえば「ひまわり」というイメージを持っている方も少なくないのではないでしょうか。
When it comes to Van Gogh, many people probably associate him with "Sunflowers".
それもそのはず、実はゴッホの描いた「ひまわり」は1つだけじゃないんです。この世界に失われたものも含めて7つの「ひまわり」があったんですよ。
And for good reason—in fact, Van Gogh didn't just paint one "Sunflowers". Including lost ones, there were seven "Sunflowers" in this world.
さて、では実際に作品をじっくり見てみましょう。
Now then, let's take a close look at the actual work.
みんなはどんな感想を持ったかな？
What kind of impressions did everyone have?
改めて見るといろんなことが見えてきます。
Looking at it again, various things become visible.
よく見るとひまわりの花の向きはバラバラで花びらも不揃いですね。
If you look closely, the directions of the sunflower flowers are all scattered and the petals are uneven.
しかし、温かな黄色が画面全体を包み込むことでどこか生命力が溢れているようにも見えませんか？
However, doesn't the warm yellow enveloping the whole screen make it look somehow full of vitality?
ここからはゴッホと黄色、そしてゴッホとひまわりについて紐解いていきましょう。
From here, let's unravel Van Gogh and yellow, as well as Van Gogh and sunflowers.
太陽は淡い耀きを伝達するもの、という言葉を残しているゴッホは、太陽の光を黄色で表現しました。
Van Gogh, who left behind the words that the sun transmits a faint radiance, expressed sunlight in yellow.
そして黄色はゴッホにとって生命力の象徴でもあります。
And yellow is also a symbol of vitality for Van Gogh.
この絵を描いた時、彼はフランス南部のアールルという町で新天地、画家として仲間と頑張っていこうと意気込んでいました。
When he painted this, in the town of Arles in southern France, he was determined to work hard as a painter in a new place with friends.
そんな気持ちを黄色に託したのかもしれません。
Perhaps he entrusted such feelings to yellow.
一方でこの絵のモチーフになっているひまわりについて見てみましょう。
On the other hand, let's look at the sunflowers which are the motif of this painting.
ひまわりは太陽に向かって咲きます。太陽は西洋美術史において神を象徴します。
Sunflowers bloom facing the sun. The sun symbolizes God in Western art history.
それに向かって咲くひまわりは崇拝、従順、忠実、そして信仰心や愛を象徴します。
Sunflowers blooming toward it symbolize worship, obedience, loyalty, and religious devotion or love.
ここでさらに遠回りして、彼の過去について知っていきましょう。
Here, let's make a further detour to learn about his past.
先ほどゴッホがアールルでの生活を始めた時、私は新天地！という表現をしました。
Earlier, when Van Gogh started his life in Arles, I used the expression "a new place!".
実は彼、元々は牧師さんになりたかったんです。
Actually, he originally wanted to become a pastor.
彼は頑張って勉強や奉仕活動に尽力しますが、うまくいきませんでした。
He tried hard and devoted himself to study and volunteer work, but it didn't go well.
画家への転身は牧師さんへの道を断たれた後のことだったんですね。
His transition to becoming a painter was something that happened after the path to becoming a pastor was cut off.
そんな彼が描く信仰の象徴であるひまわり、皆様はどう読み解きますか？
How do you interpret sunflowers, the symbol of faith painted by such a man?
未来への希望の光？それとも自分への失望？ゴッホの見た光のすみかはひまわりにあったのかもしれませんね。
A light of hope for the future? Or disappointment in himself? The dwelling of light that Van Gogh saw might have been in the sunflowers.
という感じでございまして、こちらもロンドンのナショナルギャラリーさんにて見ることができます。
With that said, this can also be seen at the National Gallery in London.
ぜひぜひ、行ってみてください！
Please, definitely go check it out!
また次回。
See you next time.
はい、ということで早いもので次が最後の曲でございますが、
Yes, with that, time flies and the next song is our final one, but
なんと！十符亭らでん新曲をリリースします！
surprise! Juufuutei Raden is releasing a new song!
新曲をリリースします！イェーイ！
A new song release! Yay!
特報！ニューシングルリリース！タイトルは……
Breaking news! New single release! The title is...
『Miracle Palette』！
"Miracle Palette"!
はい、えーこちらですね、えー楽曲リリースなんですが、
Yes, um, for this, um, song release,
5月18日の0時0分、ま、なので、今日の日付が変わった
May 18th at 00:00, so, at the timing when today's date changes,
タイミングでリリースされます。
it will be released.
5月18日といえば、そう！皆さん大世界国際博物館の日でございます！
Speaking of May 18th, right! Everyone, it's International Museum Day!
そんなね、特別な日にリリース！
Released on such a special day!
そして、この配信が終わってすぐ！MVですね、なんとミュージックビデオが公開されます、
And right after this stream ends! The MV, a music video will be released,
十符亭らでん初のダンステンコ盛り3D MVとなっております。
featuring Juufuutei Raden's first dance-packed 3D MV.
そしてこちら楽曲コンセプトはジャズっぽいね、感じになっております！ということで、
And the song concept has a jazzy feel! So,
今からライブバージョンの『Miracle Palette』を披露したいと思います！
from now on, I'd like to perform the live version of "Miracle Palette"!
ダンサーさんかもん！
Dancers, come on!
あー！よろしくお願いします！よろしくお願いします！
Ah! Thank you! Please take care of us!
ありがとう、キレキレしてくれてありがとうございます！
Thank you, thank you for doing such sharp dancing!
では、聞いてください。『Miracle Palette』！
Now, please listen. "Miracle Palette"!
暗がり ステージに立つ 雨傘を携え
Standing on a dimly lit stage, carrying an umbrella,
朧に霞む構図 印象 儚く
a hazy composition, fleeting impressions.
始めましょ 雨粒ドローイング
Let's begin, raindrop drawing.
キャンバスは この空、この世界
The canvas is this sky, this world.
hop hop 飛び回る
Hop hop, jumping around,
tap tap 打ち鳴らす
tap tap, beating out rhythm,
dance dance ぐるぐる いざショータイム
dance dance, spinning round, now it's showtime!
Ladies and Gentlemen, Welcome to our magical show!
スポットライトを浴びて 輝きを放つ
Bathed in spotlight, emitting radiance.
エンダシスよりプリズム 分光をスタンバイ
Prism over entasis, standby for dispersion.
(この鈍色の空に 七色の橋を架けて見せましょう)
(Let's paint a rainbow across this dull sky)
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Now then, behold!
目に映るもの、今を彩るから
What reflects in the eyes colors the present,
大きな絵筆で描き出す 大胆なパースの中 嗚呼
drawing with a huge paintbrush, inside a bold perspective, ah.
びしょ濡れの舞台は ミラクルなパレット
The soaked stage is a miraculous palette.
マスカレードな 第二部の開演
Masquerade, the opening of Act 2,
Shall we dance?
モノトーンから極色彩に アシンメトリーなグラデーションで
from monochrome to full color with asymmetrical gradation,
夢中になってほしいの
I want you to be lost in it.
雨雲にマーブリング
Marbling on rain clouds,
目を奪われたその隙 イリュージョンをスタンバイ
the moment your eyes are stolen, standby for illusion.
(ところで皆さん、なくしものはございませんか？)
(By the way, everyone, do you have any lost items?)
どなた様もおいでませ！
Welcome, everyone!
あの手この手で 魅了していくから
Captivating you by hook or by crook,
一足お先に まんまと盗みだすわ
stealing it smoothly just ahead of you
あなたの心を 光を放出す きらめきのパレット
your heart, emitting light, the glittering palette.
(さてさて!いよいよお勧め、クライマックスに向けて盛り上がってまいりましょう!)
(Now then! Let's get more excited toward the climax!)
Listen!
OK, 5・4・3・2・1・Go on the Show!
OK, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1, Go on the Show!
最大級のキャンバスに描き出す
Drawing on the grandest canvas,
誰も見たことのない景色
a scenery no one has ever seen.
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Now then, behold!
次元の壁を超えて 閃くから
Surpassing the dimensional wall, flashing brilliantly,
大きな絵筆で描き出す
drawing with a huge paintbrush.
大胆なパースの中さ
Painting deep within a bold perspective,
みんなで大団円 迎えに行こう
Let's go meet everyone in a grand finale!
鳴呼 びしょ濡れの舞台は ミラクルなパレット
Ah, this drenched stage is a miraculous palette!
さあさ僕とごらんあれ 目に映るもろもろ 今を彩るから
Come look with me, as everything before our eyes colors the present!
儒鳥風亭らでんがご案内「ピクセルミュージアム」追加ダウンロードコンテンツ 箱根探訪編 配信決定！
"Jufutei Raden Guides: Pixel Museum" Additional DLC "Hakone Exploration Edition" Release Confirmed!
今回のテーマは…箱根！
The theme this time is... Hakone!
らでん館長の大好きな箱根にまつわる作品をご用意しました！
We have prepared works related to Director Raden's beloved Hakone!
館内もイベント仕様で、箱根の魅力がたっぷり詰まっています！
The museum interior is also themed for the event, packed full of Hakone's charm!
もちろん解説はフルボイスでお届けしますよ！
Of course, the commentaries will be delivered in full voice!
儒鳥風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアム 追加DLC 箱根探訪編 2026年12月配信予定！
Jufutei Raden Guides: Pixel Museum Additional DLC "Hakone Exploration Edition" Scheduled for December 2026!
ちょっと待ってね！
Just wait a moment!
な、な、なんと！
W-W-What?!
昨年6月5日の発売から1年を待たずに、
Without even waiting a full year since its June 5th release last year,
儒鳥風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアムの追加DLC、箱根探訪編の配信が決定しました！
the release of additional DLC for "Jufutei Raden Guides: Pixel Museum", "Hakone Exploration Edition", has been confirmed!
やったー！
Yay!
みんながね、いっぱいダウンロードしてくれて、みんながたくさん遊んでくれたおかげです！本当にありがとうございます！
This is thanks to everyone downloading it so much and playing it a lot! Thank you so much!
今回の舞台は、皆様お馴染みの「箱根」でございます！
The stage this time is, as you all know, "Hakone"!
前作に引き続き、箱根ガラスの森美術館様に加え、今回はなんとポーラ美術館様と小田急箱根様にもご協力いただくこととなりました！拍手～！
Continuing from the previous work, in addition to the Hakone Glass Forest Museum, we are now getting cooperation from the Pola Museum of Art and Odakyu Hakone as well! Let's give a round of applause!
館長のプライベートドリームもイベント仕様にアップデート！箱根の魅力マシマシレでお届けいたします！よ、いいでしょう？
The Director's private room is also updated for the event spec! We will deliver Hakone's charm turned all the way up! Good, right?
そんな追加ダウンロードコンテンツ「箱根探訪編」は、2026年12月に配信予定！
Such additional DLC "Hakone Exploration Edition" is scheduled for release in December 2026!
さてですね、来週5月23日、24日に京都にて開催されます「ビットサミット14」にらでんぴくも登場！大好評発売中の「らでぴく」のシユや、「箱根探訪編」のキービジュアルポスターの配布もあるみたいですよ！
Now then, next week on May 23rd and 24th, Raden-Pikumu will also appear at "BitSummit 14" held in Kyoto! It seems they will also distribute key visual posters for "Radepikumu", currently on sale to great acclaim, and the "Hakone Exploration Edition"!
詳しい情報は、公式サイトとジピーターさんの公式Xを要チェックです！
Be sure to check the official website and Jupiter's official X for detailed information!
まだまだ嬉しい情報もあるかも？それではリリースまでお楽しみに！
There might still be more happy news? Well then, look forward to the release!
よい！えー、そしてそして、皆さんお待ちかね、
Excellent! Uh, and now, what you've all been waiting for,
儒鳥風亭らでん100万人記念グッズが発売されるまーす！
Jufutei Raden's 1-million-subscriber commemorative merchandise is going on sale!
やったー！
Yay!
お前ね、今日本当になんか発表が多くて、えー早速詳細見ていきましょう！1つ目はこちラでん。
Man, there are really so many announcements today, uh, let's check the details right away! The first one is right here.
新衣装でライブ！アクリルブロック。いやめっちゃ疲れてるらでんが写っちゃった。新衣装でライブアクリルブロック！ライブステージで楽しそうに歌う新衣装のらでん。森倉円先生の描き下ろしでございます！いいでしょう！こちらアクリルブロックの表裏に印刷されております。
Live in new costume! Acrylic block. Man, a really tired-looking Raden got captured. Live in new costume acrylic block! Raden in her new costume singing happily on the live stage. Illustrated by Circle Morkura! Isn't it great? This is printed on both the front and back of the acrylic block.
めっちゃね奥行きが感じられるものとなっているんですよ。
It's made so you can really feel the depth.
続いてはこちららでん！はい、らでんの衣装いろいろ3連結アクリルキーホルダー。新衣装通常衣装クラッシュポイント衣装の3種類の3連結アクリルキーホルダーとなっております。イラストは心パズルリズムのときのね、後ろにかわいいイラストが流れてたんですけど、お馴染みちぽミルク先生でございます！
Next is this one! Yes, Raden's various outfits 3-linked acrylic keychain. It consists of 3-linked acrylic keychains of 3 types: new outfit, standard outfit, and crash point outfit. The illustration is by our familiar Chipo Milk-sensei, from when "Heart Puzzle Rhythm" was playing cute illustrations in the background!
続いてはこちららでん！新衣装モチーフピンバッジセット。新衣装をモチーフにしたピンバッジセットですよ。懐中時計、えーそれから、えー懐中時計、えーそれから今してないけどマスク、えーシルクハット、えーモノクルの4種類となっております。
Next is this one! New costume motif pin badge set. It's a pin badge set themed around the new costume. It consists of 4 types: a pocket watch, um, and then, um, pocket watch, um, and then a mask (though I'm not wearing it now), silk hat, and monocle.
続いてはこちららでん！ライブ前のトラブル！？ボイス。らでんが書き下ろした台本です。どんなトラブルが…
Next is this one! "Trouble before the live!?" Voice. It's a script written by Raden. What kind of trouble...
グルナの川聴いてみてのお楽しみ。
Look forward to listening to the Guruna River audio!
そしてフルセット購入特典はこちらです。
And here are the full set purchase benefits.
はい、えー十風てらでん直筆サイン入りモリクラ先生描き下ろしポストカード。
A signed postcard with an illustration by Mori Kura-sensei!
今回もご購入いただいた方全員に、直筆でサインを書かせていただきますよ！
This time too, I'll personally hand-sign copies for everyone who purchases it!
皆さんに届くように精一杯書かせていただくので、よろしくお願いいたします！
I'll sign each one with all my heart so it reaches you all, so please look forward to it!
さらに、特典ボイスも付きます。こちらもてらでんが書き下ろしてます。
Plus, bonus voice packs! Those are also written by Teraden.
はいという形で、もう今日ね、もうすご、すごい盛りだくさんでございましたが、
So with all that, today was super, super packed with content,
皆さん追いつけてますか？
but are you all keeping up?
結構とんでもないね、発表をたくさんしたんですけれども、てらでんが一番結構とんでもないなと思っております。
I made quite a few crazy announcements, but I think mine is probably the craziest!
ということで、本日の重大発表は、その1、東京国立博物館さんとのコラボ。
So, today's major announcements: #1, collaboration with the Tokyo National Museum.
その2、ロンドンナショナルギャラリーさんとのコラボ。
#2, collaboration with the London National Gallery.
その3、十風てらでんご案内ピクセルミュージアムダウンロードコンテンツ発売決定でございます。
#3, release of Pixel Museum DLC guided by Jufu Teraden!
情報量がね、多すぎたと思うので、ぜひアーカイブでも確認してみてください。
That was a lot of info, so please be sure to check the archive too.
そしてこの後はメン限でアンコールライブあります！その時にまた衣装はね、ゆっくりお見せしようかなと思っておりますので、
And after this, there's a member-only encore live! I'll show you the outfit slowly during that time,
まだの方のチャンネル登録と、え、気になるよって方はメンバーでね、またアンコールライブでお会いしましょう。
so for those who haven't subscribed yet, and those interested, let's meet again in the encore live!
そしてそして忘れちゃいけません！この後すぐ新曲MV公開でございます！
And we mustn't forget! Right after this, the new song MV premieres!
頑張って作ったんで、いっぱい見てほしいです！
I worked hard on it, so I really want you all to watch it!
ということでございまして、え、日頃応援してくださっている皆々様、見ていただいている聞いていただいているリスナーの皆様のおかげで、今回ね、このライブを開催することができました。本当に本当にありがとうございます！とっても嬉しいです！
So, thanks to everyone who supports me every day, and all the listeners watching and listening, we were able to hold this live today. Thank you so much, truly! I'm so happy!
これからもね、歌もね、ダンスも、自分のね、やりたいことも、いっぱい頑張っていきますので、ぜひ応援の方よろしくお願いいたします。
From now on too, I'll work hard on singing, dancing, and everything I want to do, so please continue to support me!
それではメンゲンアンコールライブで思いっきりいたしましょう！本日ののお相手は私十風てらでんでした。
Now then, let's enjoy the member-only encore live to the fullest! Today's host was me, Jufu Teraden.
それでは皆さん、良い夜をお過ごしください。さようならー！
Well everyone, have a wonderful evening. Goodbye!